<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Recent Articles on AakEz</title>
    <link>https://aakash-ez.github.io/off-topic/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Recent Articles on AakEz</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 13:00:00 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aakash-ez.github.io/off-topic/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>CSK 2021: A Statistical Review</title>
      <link>https://aakash-ez.github.io/off-topic/csk-2021-ipl-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 13:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aakash-ez.github.io/off-topic/csk-2021-ipl-review/</guid>
      <description>After a disappointing 2020 season, the team led by MS Dhoni performed significantly better, winning their fourth title. Consistent performance across both the legs of the tournament along with the openers giving a great base for the team to build their innings on certainly were the factors that contributed towards their success. In this post, I hope to look into some of these factors.
Openers Shining It&amp;rsquo;s not hard to understand why opener&amp;rsquo;s form is crucial for a team&amp;rsquo;s success.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IPL 2021: A Statistical Review</title>
      <link>https://aakash-ez.github.io/off-topic/ipl-2021-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Oct 2021 13:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aakash-ez.github.io/off-topic/ipl-2021-review/</guid>
      <description>India&amp;rsquo;s T20 cricket league, IPL&amp;rsquo;s 2021 edition recently concluded with Chennai Super Kings winning their 4th title. The season was certainly a unique one, having been conducted in two legs due to covid. Further we also saw a bunch of new players coming through like Gaikwad, Venkatesh, CV Varun etc. In this post, I am hoping to take a look back at the event, from a statistical point of view.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When A Machine beat Kasparov</title>
      <link>https://aakash-ez.github.io/off-topic/when-a-machine-beat-kasparov/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Aug 2021 15:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aakash-ez.github.io/off-topic/when-a-machine-beat-kasparov/</guid>
      <description>I am writing this article as I read the book &amp;ldquo;Deep Thinking&amp;rdquo; by Garry Kasparov. The book deals with his experience/experiments with AI and how it had evolved over time, from being significantly weaker than chess Grandmasters, to beating one of the greatest players, Kasparov himself.
Introduction Chess has been one of the most commonly considered problems in AI domain. Almost anyone who has worked in AI has dwelled into chess and developed a model which can play reasonable chess.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Started with Google Football</title>
      <link>https://aakash-ez.github.io/off-topic/getting-started-with-google-football/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +1800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aakash-ez.github.io/off-topic/getting-started-with-google-football/</guid>
      <description>Football (or Soccer) is the most popular sport on earth with over 3.572 billion people tuning in for the last world cup finals. It also is a unique AI problem due its continuous, multi-agent nature and a wide array of actions possible in every moment. Google Brain, a deep learning / artificial intelligence research team at Google, implemented a Football Environment for developers and researchers to experiment various Reinforcement learning models.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Engineering Materials For Efficient Heat Dissipation In Aerospace</title>
      <link>https://aakash-ez.github.io/off-topic/heat-dissipation-in-aerospace/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +1800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aakash-ez.github.io/off-topic/heat-dissipation-in-aerospace/</guid>
      <description>What Is Heat Dissipation? Transfer of energy from a more concentrated form (Hotter) to less concentrated form (Colder) simply is heat dissipation. It is an irreversible process and its always associated with an increase in entropy thus making this process entropically favorable.
Importance Of Efficient Heat Dissipation Systems  For maintaining optimum working temperature To improves efficiency of the system To Increases the working life of the equipment And above all its required to ensure Safety  Figure 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chess using Python3</title>
      <link>https://aakash-ez.github.io/off-topic/chess-using-python3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +1800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aakash-ez.github.io/off-topic/chess-using-python3/</guid>
      <description>Chess is among the most popular board games on Earth, with a history of over thousands of years. It has also been one of the most widely studied games in the domain of AI, due to its strategic nature. This has lead to the development of many advanced chess engines which has the ability to even beat world champions (Deep Blue versus Garry Kasparov, 1997).
Today, I want to discuss about a python library I found which could visualize chess boards, help identify the possible legal moves etc.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
